现在我有我的机器人和坐标框架，我可以测量机器人的位置
Now that I have my robot and a coordinate frame, I can measure the position of the robot
相对于坐标系。所以，用我的卷尺，我可以看到机器人
with respect to the coordinate frame. So, with my tape measure, I can see that the robot
有一个18厘米的x坐标，它有一个16厘米的坐标。
has got an x coordinate of 18 centimetres and it has got a y coordinate of 16 centimetres.
所以我可以用矢量和元素来描述机器人的位置
So I can describe the position of the robot in terms of a vector and the elements of the
矢量是以厘米为单位的18和16。现在，我可以介绍其他对象了
vector are 18 and 16 in units of centimetres. Now, I can introduce other objects in the
环境。一个机器人可以有一个小朋友。他的小朋友可以坐在那里，并且
environment. A robot can have a little friend. His little friend can sit over there, and
我也可以衡量这位小朋友的位置。并且，他坐在大约38厘米
I can measure the position of the little friend as well. And, he is sitting at about 38 centimetres
在x方向，这是他的x坐标。并且，y坐标，不容易测量，
in the x direction, that’s his x coordinate. And, the y coordinate, not so easy to measure,
但我可以说也许它在y方向上是6厘米。所以，其中的任何对象
but I could say perhaps it’s 6 centimetres in the y direction. So, any object within
在这个环境中，我可以用两个坐标来描述它们的位置
this environment I can describe their position in terms of two coordinates with respect to
我在开头放下的坐标框架。
the coordinate frame that I laid down at the beginning.
描述机器人的位置是问题的一个重要部分，但它是
Describing the position of the robot is an important part of the problem, but it’s
还不够。我们需要能够说出这个机器人面临的方式。
not quite enough. We need to be able to say something about which way this robot is facing.
所以，如果这个机器人想要移动到这个机器人，我们需要知道它是否正在进行
So, if this robot wanted to move towards this robot, we need to know whether it’s going
向前，向左，向右，向后移动。所以，这个机器人非常不同
to move forwards, to the left, to the right, backwards. So, this robot is very different
对这个机器人，对这个机器人，对这个机器人。能够描述哪个是很重要的
to this robot, to this robot, to this robot. It’s important to be able to describe which
这是面临的方式。并且，为了描述它面临的方式，我们可以使用这些工具
way it’s facing. And, in order to describe which way it’s facing, we can use the tools
我们已经讨论过了。而且，我们能做的是我们可以附加另一个坐标
that we've already been discussing. And, what we can do is we can attach another coordinate
框架到我们的机器人。在这种情况下，我将使用绿色坐标框架，我是
frame to our robot. In this case, I’m going to use a green coordinate frame and I’m
用一些蓝色大头钉将它贴在机器人的底部。现在
going to stick it on to the bottom of the robot with some, with some blue tack. Now
对于这里的机器人，我们可以描述它的方向-它面对的方式
with the robots here, we can describe its orientation - the way it’s facing in the
world-通过该坐标系相对于该坐标系的方向。
world - by the orientation of this coordinate frame with respect to this coordinate frame.
那么，我们可以描述我们所附加的这个新坐标系的位置
So, we can describe then the position of this new coordinate frame that we've attached to
机器人在运动方面。我们从原始坐标框架进行运动，我们的参考
the robot in terms of a motion. We do a motion from the original coordinate frame, our reference
坐标框架，有时称为世界坐标框架，我们移动原点
coordinate frame, sometimes called the world coordinate frame, that we move the origin
这个框架到这里然后我们旋转。我们可以为小机器人做同样的事情。
of this frame to here and then we rotate. We can do the same thing for the little robot.
我们可以描述它相对于世界坐标系的姿势。要做到这一点，我是
We can describe its pose with respect to the world coordinate frame. To do that, I’m
要将蓝色坐标框架附加到这个小机器人身上，我要去定位
going to attach a blue coordinate frame to this little robot, and, I’m going to orient
它使x轴指向前方。这是一个非常常见的惯例
it so that the x-axis is pointing forward. And this is a pretty common convention for
飞机，船舶，汽车，机器人。我们使x轴成为机器正常运动的方向。
airplane, ships, cars, robots. We make the x-axis the direction of normal motion for the machine.
现在，我们有一个非常简单的表示
Now, we have a very simple representation
现在描述的原始环境完全是根据多个坐标来描述的
of the original environment where it’s described now entirely in terms of a number of coordinate
表示该环境中重要实体的姿势的框架
frames which represent the pose of the important entities in that environment with respect
到世界坐标框架。现在，就像我们为大型机器人所做的那样，我们可以考虑
to the world coordinate frame. Now, just as we did for the big robot, we can consider
这个小机器人在运动方面的姿势。所以，想象一下我们移动坐标
the pose of the little robot in terms of a motion. So, imagine that we move the coordinate
它位于参考坐标系顶部的框架。我们做翻译
frame from where it lies on top of the reference coordinate frame. We make a translational
运动，水平移动，我们垂直移动，然后旋转它并旋转它
motion, move it horizontally, we move it vertically, and then we rotate it and rotate it quite
一点直到它位于该坐标系的顶部。所以，这就是小小的姿势
a bit until it lies on top of that coordinate frame. So, that is the pose of the little
机器人相对于根据位置分量描述的世界坐标系
robot with respect to the world coordinate frame described in terms of a positional component
和旋转部件。所以，现在我们已经描述了它的姿势
and a rotational component. So, now we have described the pose of the
相对于世界坐标框架的小机器人。我们之前描述过的姿势
little robot with respect to the world coordinate frame. We previously described the pose of
关于世界坐标系的大机器人。但是，我们也可以描述姿势
the big robot with respect to the world coordinate frame. But, we can also describe the pose
关于大机器人的小机器人，我们可以通过拿起机器人做到这一点
of the little robot with respect to the big robot, and we can do that by picking up the
大机器人的坐标框架，我们在世界x方向上进行翻译，并且
big robot’s coordinate frame and we make a translation in the world x direction, and
然后在世界y方向，然后我们旋转它直到轴线向上。然后
then in the world y direction, and then we rotate it until the axis line up. And, that
然后是从这个坐标系到这个坐标系的相对运动或相对姿势。
then is a relative motion or relative pose from this coordinate frame to this one.
我将使用这个希腊字母，发音为ksi来表示姿势。在
I’m going to use this Greek letter which is pronounced as ksi to represent pose. In
一个二维世界，pose有三个参数：x和y代表偏移量
a two-dimensional world, pose has got three parameters: x and y which represent the offset
从一个坐标系的原点到下一个坐标系的原点，和
from the origin of one coordinate frame to the origin of the next coordinate frame, and
角度θ表示从一个坐标系到下一个坐标系的旋转。那里
the angle Theta which represents the rotation from one coordinate frame to the next. There
当我们谈论一个坐标系的旋转时，这是一个重要的约定
is an important convention when we talk about the rotation of one coordinate frame with
相对于另一个，也就是角度在逆时针方向上正向增加。
respect to another, and that is that angles increase positively in the anticlockwise direction.
所以，如果这是我的原始坐标系，如果我按角度Theta旋转它，它看起来
So, if this is my original coordinate frame, if I rotate that by the angle Theta, it looks
像这样。重要的是，正向旋转处于逆时针方向。
like this. Importantly, positive rotation is in the anticlockwise direction.
我们还可以将姿势视为移动，x方向和y方向的运动，
We can also think about pose as a move, a motion in the x direction and in the y direction,
然后通过量Theta旋转或扭曲。
and then a rotation or twist by the amount Theta.
因此，我们可以描述我们附加的这个新坐标系的位置
So, we can describe that the position of this new coordinate frame that we have attached
在运动方面对机器人。我们从原始坐标系做一个动作，
to the robot in terms of a motion. We do a motion from the original coordinate frame,
我们的参考坐标框架，有时也称为世界坐标框架
our reference coordinate frame, sometimes called the world coordinate frame, that we
将此框架的原点移动到此处，然后我们旋转。
move the origin of this frame to here, and then we rotate.
那么，让我们总结一下我们在本节中介绍的内容。一点可以用来描述
So, let’s summarise what we've covered in this section. A point can be described by
关于特定坐标系的向量，当我们这样做时，我们介绍
a vector with respect to a particular coordinate frame, and, when we do that, we introduce
一些额外的表示法。我们使用符号小写p来表示向量。A
some additional notation. We use the symbol lower case p to represent a vector. The A
infront表示向量开始的坐标系。所以，这个向量开始了
in front denotes the coordinate frame from which the vector starts. So, this vector begins
从坐标框架A的原点开始。尾随B是目的地。就是这样
from the origin of coordinate frame A. The trailing B is the destination. It’s the
向量指向的点的名称。可以描述坐标系的姿势
name of the point that the vector points to. The pose of a coordinate frame can be described
相对于另一个坐标系。我用这个胖箭来表示姿势
with respect to another coordinate frame. I used this fat arrow to represent the pose
-从坐标系A到坐标系B的运动。现在，运动比复杂
- the motion from coordinate frame A to coordinate frame B. Now, the motion is more complex than
只是一个普通的矢量翻译。它包括翻译和轮换，
just a translation like an ordinary vector. It includes a translation and a rotation,
这就是为什么我使用了不同类型的箭头。你知道它更胖，而且它是
so that’s why I used a different kind of arrow. You know that it’s fatter and it’s
有一种不同的头脑。象征性地，我这样形容它。我用
got a different kind of head. Symbolically, I describe it like this. I use
希腊字母ksi表示我们正在谈论一个姿势。领先的A是
the Greek letter ksi to denote that we’re talking about a pose. The leading A is the
参照系。这就是我从哪里开始的。尾随B是我想要结束的地方
frame of reference. That’s where I start from. The trailing B is where I want to end
起来。该符号描述了相对运动，即坐标系的相对姿态
up. This symbol describes a relative motion, a relative pose from the coordinate frame
A到坐标系B.我们可以将姿势视为运动。我们可以将其视为
A to the coordinate frame B. We can consider a pose as a motion. We can consider it as
翻译和轮换。并且，对于二维情况，描述姿势
a translation and a rotation. And, for the two-dimensional case, the pose is described
由三个数字组成：两个平移分量和一个旋转分量。
by three numbers: two translational components and one rotational component.